A Guide to the Social Science Research Council records, Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS), Record Group 3, Series 3 FA1483
Rockefeller Archive Center
Social Science Research Council records, Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS), Record Group 3, Series 3
1959, 1983-1991
Rockefeller Archive Center
Social Science Research Council
FA1483
5.32 Cubic Feet 14 letter-size document boxes.
Arrangement
The Social Science Research Council archives are arranged into three record groups distinguished by the date of their donation to the Archive Center. Accession 1 (Record Group 1) consists of the documents received by the Archive Center in 1990; Accession 2 (Record Group 2) was transferred to the Archive Center in 1994; Record Group 3 was transferred to the Archive Center in 2017-2018.
Within series the records are primarily arranged in original order.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Social Science Research Council records were donated to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1990 and record transfers continue periodically. The records in this series were received in 2017-2018.
Biographical / Historical
The Social Science Research Council (SSRC) is a private, not-for-profit organization established in 1923 to advance research in the social sciences. The SSRC came into being through the initiatives of Wesley C. Mitchell and Charles E. Merriam, members of the American Political Science Association. Representatives of the American Economic Association, the American Sociological Society, the American Statistical Association, the American Historical Association and the American Psychological Association assisted Merriam and his associates in forming the SSRC. They invited the participation of other national associations in anthropology, history, and psychology, many of which designated representatives to the SSRC in the year following its incorporation on December 27, 1924.
To support its work, the SSRC turned not to the U.S. government, whose support seemed more appropriate for the natural sciences, but to private foundations. For the first fifty years, well over three-quarters of the SSRC's funding was provided by the Russell Sage Foundation, the Ford Foundation, the Carnegie Corporation, and two Rockefeller philanthropies, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial and the Rockefeller Foundation. By the 1970s, however, funds for some special projects were obtained from federal agencies.
Other Finding Aids
Other finding aids documenting Social Science Research Council records include:
FA021 Social Science Research Council records, Record Group 1 and Record Group 2 FA1196 Social Science Research Council records, Economics Intiative, RG 3, Series 1
Scope and Contents
The vast majority of the AIDS series is comprised of the files of Richard C. Rockwell. Records include project proposals, conference papers and proposals, survey files, meeting records, correspondence and other research materials.
- AIDS, 1959, 1983-1991; 3
  - The Milbank Quarterly, Volume 68, Supplement 1 and 2 - A Disease of Society: Cultural Responses to AIDS, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - IV International Conference on Aids, Book 1: Final Program, Stockholm, Sweden, 1988 June 12-16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IV International Conference on Aids, Book 2: Program and Abstracts, Stockholm, Sweden, 1988 June 12-16 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 2016:004:008 and 2016:004:009 - AIDS in Africa: The Social and Policy Impact - bound volumes (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Special format items have been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
  - SIDA: 혨PID혨MIES ET SOCI혨T혨S - AIDS: Epidemics and Societies, 1987 June 20-21 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AIDS and Society - International Research and Policy Bulletin, 1990 October-November (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Summary: AIDS - The Second Decade, Henry G. Miller, Charles F. Turner and Lincoln E. Moses, Editors, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - IV International Conference on Aids - List of Participants, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Richard C. Rockwell - The Association of Pharmacists and Corporate America for AIDS Education (APCA) Advisory Board, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legal Docket: AIDS and the Law, Sexuality and the Law, ACLU, 1987 July (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Epidemiology, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Methodology, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Education, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Policy-Legislation, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Minorities, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - Effect, Consequences, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - AIDS Survey - Papers - International, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Social Research, Volume 55, No. 3 - In Time of Plague: The History and Social Consequences of Lethal Epidemic Disease, 1988 Autumn (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Confronting AIDS: Directions for Public Health, Health Care, and Research - Summary and Recommendations, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic - Hearing On: Response to the Pandemic by the United States, 1988 April 18-20 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - DAEDALUS: Living with AIDS, 1989 Spring (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Retroviruses of Human AIDS and Related Animal Diseases, Colloque Des Cent Gardes, Paris, France, 1988 October 27-29 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - AIDS and Society - International Research and Policy Bulletin, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Social and Behavioral Aspects of Health and Fertility-Related Behavior - Technical Proposal, NORC, University of Chicago, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Committee on AIDS Research - Articles, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - National Survey of Health and Sexual Behavior Meeting, 1990 February 13 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Committee on AIDS Research - Evaluating AIDS Prevention Programs, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - World Health Organization - Global Program on AIDS, 1987-1989 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Pretest of a Questionnaire on the Social and Behavioral Aspects of Health and Fertility-Related Behavior in a Population of 2,000 Adult Men and Women, NORDC (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - National Survey of Health and Sexual Behavior (NHSB) Home Study Cover Memo (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Social Impacts of the HIV Epidemic, Richard C. Rockwell (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Report of the Presidential Commission on the Human Immunodeficiency Virus Epidemic, 1988 June (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Science Journal, Volume 239, 1988 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - AIDS - World Health Organization, 1983-1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - WHO Western Journal of Medicine and Surgery (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Index of Papers, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 24 - Epidemiology, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 25 - Methodology, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 26 - Education (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 27 - Programs-Services, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 28 - Policy-Legislation, 1987-1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 29 - Minorities, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 30 - Effects-Consequences, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - AIDS Information Gathering Survey - Paper No. 31 - International, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - AIDS - An International Bimonthly Journal, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - National Leadership Coalition on AIDS (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - United Nations - World AIDS Day, 1988-1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Richard C. Rockwell - Survey of Income and Program Participation (SIPP), 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - WHO - Malaria, 1959-1986 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Global Social Consequences of AIDS Meeting, 1988 October 21 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Public Health Reports (Journal of the U.S. Public Health Service) - The Response to AIDS, Vol. 103, No. 3, 1988 May-June (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - AIDS Shelter Project Final Report (Institute of Public Services Performance, Inc.), 1986 January (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Journal of the American Medical Association (JAMA) - AIDS from the Beginning, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Richard C. Rockwell Files - AIDS Papers and Proposals, 1986-1990 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - The Society for the Scientific Study of Sex: Membership Info. And National Health Interview Survey (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Richard C. Rockwell - Chronological File, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - AIDS Bib: Gallo, R. The AIDS Virus, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - AIDS - Gay Men's Health Crisis Materials, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Blurb for SSRC: Mental health issues in AIDS, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - AIDS Bib: Jill Joseph Papers (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Richard C. Rockwell - Chicago Meeting - Electronic Mail (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Douglas Feldman, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Francis Paine Conant - Proposals, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Canada AIDS Research Centers (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) - Organizational Database, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Richard Berk - AIDS Proposals, 1987 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - AIDS Project Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Impacts for the Social Sciences of AIDS (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Don Guthrie - Editor, JASA (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - JASA Reviews, 1990 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - JASA - Social Statistics and Public Policy - Special Section, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - JASA Special Section Committee - Prospectus, Wave 1 Response, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - JASA Special Section Materials, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - JASA Special Section - Boruch (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - JASA Special Section - Corder, 1989-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - JASA Special Section - Pearson, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - JASA Special Section - Schirm (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - JASA Special Section - Shelley, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - JASA Special Section - Mason, Wong, 1989-1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Random AIDS articles II (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Sex Study (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Sex Study Results (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Many Questions, Few Answers (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Carballo, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Gerald Desmond Interview (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Global Social Aspects of AIDS - Original, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Norman Miller, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - AIDS Research Financial Report, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Global AIDS Bulletin (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - United Nations AIDS Advisory Group (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Social Impact of AIDS: What Themes, Why Pursue, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Richard C. Rockwell - Recommendations for the Presidential Commission (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - AIDS Meeting - Notes, Doral, 1988 October (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - WHO - Global Programme on AIDS (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - AIDS Operation Snowball, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - AIDS Survey, 1987-1990 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - AIDS General Correspondence, 1989 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - AIDS Survey Correspondence, 1988 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Social Consequences of AIDS Proposal, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - AIDS Newsletters, 1986-1989 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Social Consequences of AIDS Proposal, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Update on SSRC AIDS Project, 1988-1989 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Social Consequences of AIDS Proposal, 1987-1988 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Social Consequences of AIDS - Draft, 1987 June (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - AIDS - Articles, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - AIDS - Articles and Pamphlets, 1985-1987 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - AIDS Meeting - Participants and Agenda, 1986 May 13 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - AIDS Meeting - Participants, 1986 September 26 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - AIDS Meeting - Circulated Material, 1986 September 26 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Civic Discourse - Draft Letters for Committee Participants (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Civic Discourse - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Civic Discourse - Network, 1984-1986 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Civic Discourse - Drafts (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Civic Discourse - Proposal - AIDS (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Civic Discourse - References, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Civic Discourse - Mary Douglas Paper, 1986 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Civic Discourse - Papers (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Civic Discourse - Appendix to the Board, 1985 November 20 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Civic Discourse - Budget, 1985-1986 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Possible Funders (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Civic Discourse (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - The Humanities and Social Sciences - Jennings (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Civic Discourse Meeting - Exxon, 1984 July 13 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Civic Discourse Meeting - Exxon, 1984 June 18-19 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Civic Discourse - Articles, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Civic Discourse - Working File, 1984 (Box 14, Folder 5)